<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>W.M.Moon</title>
    <description>A collection of thoughts on science, sports, and other fun stuff.
</description>
    <link>http://wmmoon.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://wmmoon.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jan 2017 12:56:07 -0600</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 27 Jan 2017 12:56:07 -0600</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.2.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Kobe Over the Years</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Those who know me know that I’m a huge basketball fan. And now that my playing days are over, I have transitioned from playing basketball to the even more exciting activity of analyzing basketball data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll be writing my first post on one of basketball’s greatest icons, Kobe Bryant. Considered one of the greatest and most popular players to every play the game, he is particularly interesting because of his ability to stay dominant for so many years. He was able to do so, not only by being gifted with great genes and working extremely hard, but also by being smart and changing his style of play throughout his career to adjust to the changes in the NBA, his teammates, and his own body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the sake of this post, I will divide Kobe’s career into five different eras. First, we call the first three years of Kobe’s career as the &lt;a href=&quot;https://i.ytimg.com/vi/eaJMLnt5bdU/maxresdefault.jpg&quot;&gt;“Young Kobe”&lt;/a&gt; era, which is followed by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://static1.squarespace.com/static/564173e3e4b047c0f3f64775/t/570e96fd27d4bd2e542dfb32/1460573954240/&quot;&gt;“Frobe”&lt;/a&gt; era, during which Kobe rocked his famous afro. After that we have &lt;a href=&quot;http://s3.amazonaws.com/tpt-uploads-production/uploads/56704175-copy-3-e1453399062311.jpg&quot;&gt;“Solo Kobe”&lt;/a&gt; during which he had his historical 81 point game (in which Kwame Brown played &lt;a href=&quot;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/Cf-ATfBWIAAOkQ5.jpg&quot;&gt;32 minutes&lt;/a&gt;). Then we have &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.rantsports.com/nba/files/2015/03/Kobe-Bryant.jpg&quot;&gt;“Black Mamba”&lt;/a&gt; Kobe followed by &lt;a href=&quot;http://i.cdn.turner.com/nba/nba/.element/media/2.0/teamsites/lakers/images/press/1213_allstar/ts_010103allstar670.jpg&quot;&gt;“Vino”&lt;/a&gt; Kobe. (These names and eras were inspired by a reddit post I read a while ago)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First let us take a look at his shooting percentages from different distances during each of these eras.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/wmoon5/wmoon5.github.io/blob/master/images/kobe/FGPct_ShotZones.png?raw=true&quot; alt=&quot;Kobe fgpct barchart&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice Kobe’s drastic improvement in the in the 8-16 ft. range. Anyone who watched Kobe during the second half of his career has seen shots like &lt;a href=&quot;https://68.media.tumblr.com/dfb8b3148d2e327bf306064f835cd569/tumblr_o3zj3nVBtk1s3gys4o1_400.gif&quot;&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt; countless times and it’s exactly this improved mid-range game that allowed Kobe to remain an elite player for so long. Also, interestingly enough, we can see Kobe’s percentages in the 24+ ft. range decrease fairly consistently, which I wasn’t expecting because I had always thought his three point shooting improved throughout his career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, how about we look at how often Kobe was shooting from these distances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/wmoon5/wmoon5.github.io/blob/master/images/kobe/ShotZones_Pie.png?raw=true&quot; alt=&quot;Kobe shot distance distribution&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To me, the most obvious trend is the decrease in shots from fewer than 8 ft. away. Presumably a large portion of these shots are from driving and attacking the basket, which is taxing on the body and thus more difficult for older players. I also find it interesting to notice that only Solo Kobe shot more than half of his shots from more than 16 ft. away. Solo Kobe also happened to be the version of Kobe with the highest rate of scoring, clocking in at a whopping 35.4 points per game in his ‘05-‘06 season. However, he was also shooting way more shots per game that season than any of his other seasons, so my interpretation is that most of the extra shots he was taking that season and during the Solo Kobe era were from greater distances because generally it takes less energy to pull up for a long range jumper than having to battle a defender for position and take a shot from closer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can confirm some of these trends by looking at the types of shots Kobe was shooting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/wmoon5/wmoon5.github.io/blob/master/images/kobe/ShotTypes_Pie.png?raw=true&quot; alt=&quot;Kobe shot types distribution&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we can see more obviously the increase in jump shooting and the decrease in layups and dunks throughout Kobe’s career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None of this is very groundbreaking. Basketball fans know that Kobe was an athletic freak and could rise up and put you on a poster on any given night, but what made him special was his ability to work on the other parts of his game that would allow him to continue to be dominant as he got older. Another player that comes to mind who has similarly transformed his game is Vince Carter (who just turned 40 by the way and is still doing stuff like &lt;a href=&quot;http://streamable.com/6ebnr&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, for the basketball fans out there. Which Kobe was your favorite Kobe? (My answer: Black Mamba)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jan 2017 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://wmmoon.com/2017/01/26/Kobe.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://wmmoon.com/2017/01/26/Kobe.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
